Guide to the Donald Oenslager Collection of Adolphe Appia
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Donald Oenslager collection of Adolphe Appia
1892-1971
1920-1926
GEN MSS 81
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1
(2 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
The papers contian correspondence, manuscripts, articles, and miscellaneous papers, documenting the life and career of Adolphe Appia. The papers were collected by Donald Oenslager, professor at the Yale School of Drama.
Appia, Adolphe, 1862-1928
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Donald Oenslager, 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Adolphe Appia (1862-1928)
Adolphe François Appia was born in Geneva, the son of Louis Paul Amédée Appia, a successful surgeon and one of the founders of the Red Cross. While a youth, he became fascinated with the theater, but since his family considered it an inappropriate career choice, he studied music at Geneva, Paris, Leipzig, and Dresden.
In 1884 Appia met Houston Stewart Chamberlain and became devoted to the works of Richard Wagner. With the help and encouragement of Chamberlain, he decided to become a designer and stage director.
Although he received scant recognition during his lifetime, Appia is regarded today as the father of modern stage lighting and design. His reforms of the antiquated nineteenth-century practice of stage design emphasized the significance of time and space, the relation of stage and auditorium, and the contrast of light and shadow. He devoted much of his lifework in particular to creating new productions of the operas of Richard Wagner.
Appia died on February 29, 1928, in a nursing home near Nyon, Switzerland.
Appia set down his theories on stage set design in two books and several essays, but much of his writing was published only in the 1950s and 1960s. The Fondation Adolphe Appia has as its objective the publication of all his works and the furtherance of his ideas.
For further biographical information, see Walther R. Volbach's Adolphe Appia, Prophet of the Modern Theatre: A Profile (1968).
Scope and Contents
The Donald Oenslager Collection of Adolphe Appia contains correspondence, holograph and typescript manuscripts, articles, miscellaneous papers and drawings documenting the life and career of the author of Die Musik und die Inscenierung (1899). The material spans the years 1900 to 1971, with the bulk falling between 1920 and 1926. The papers were collected by Donald Oenslager, who wrote on stage and theater design and taught in the Yale School of Drama for over forty years.
The first section of the collection contains Oenslager's correspondence concerning Appia. Letters between Oenslager and Edmond Appia, distant cousin of Adolphe and representative of the Fondation Adolphe Appia, document the purchase of the typescript carbons of Appia's essays which are found in the second section of the collection. Correspondence between Oenslager and Samuel J. Hume, an author on the theater and dealer in rare books on the subject in Berkeley, California, relates in part to the purchase of Appia manuscripts. A third folder contains correspondence between Oenslager and Walther R. Volbach, a fellow Appia enthusiast and author of Adolphe Appia, Prophet of the Modern Theatre: A Profile.
The second section, Writings, includes over twenty essays by Appia, and an outline of La musique et la mise en scène together with an English translation of that work, based on the German version. Most examples are typescript drafts. The section begins with a list (folder 4) which provides a brief description of most of the writings. All the material in this section except the manuscripts in folders 8, 10, 23, and 24 were bought by Oenslager from the Fondation Adolphe Appia in 1953 and bear the mark of the Fondation. They are third carbons (of six).
The third section,Writings about Appia, contains over a dozen articles by such writers as Carl Niessen, Edmund Stadler, Carl Van Vechten, Jessica Davis Van Wyck, and Walther R. Volbach. Included in this section are two issues of theater magazines dedicated to the memory of Appia.
The fourth section, Miscellaneous Papers, contains materials relating to Emile Jaques-Dalcroze, a Swiss education reformer with whom Appia collaborated, and photographs of Appia.
The fifth section, Drawings, contains three set design drawings for Wagner's Ring Cycle.
Opera -- Production and direction; Theater -- Production and direction; Theaters -- Stage-setting and scenery; Drawings (visual works) -- Switzerland -- 19th century; Opera producers and directors; Set designers; Appia, Adolphe, 1862-1928; Appia, Edmond, 1894-1961; Hume, Samuel J. (Samuel James), 1885-1962; Jaques-Dalcroze, Émile, 1865-1950; Oenslager, Donald, 1902-1975; Volbach, Walther R. (Walther Richard), 1897-1996; Wagner, Richard, 1813-1883 ( Performances)
- Correspondence, 1953-1970
  - Appia, Edmond, 1953-61 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hume, Samuel J., 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Volbach, Walther R., 1961-70 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Writings, 1900-1929
  - Liste de textes inédits importants d'Adolphe Appia: typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "L'art dramatique vivant": typescript, carbon, corrected, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "L'art est une attitude": typescript, carbon, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Art vivant ou nature morte": typescript, carbon, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Art vivant ou nature morte": printed version, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Avertissement pour l'édition de mes 'essais' en un volume": typescript, carbon, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Comment réformer notre mise en scène": holograph, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Comment réformer notre mise en scène": typescript, carbon, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Curriculum vitae d'Adolphe Appia, écrit par lui-même en 1927": typescript (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Devons-nous (ou pourrons-nous ???) réaliser l'idéal de Wagner?": typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Expériences de théâtre et recherches personnelles": typescript, carbon, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Formes nouvelles": typescript, carbon, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "L'homme est la mesure de toutes choses (Protagoras), préface à un nouvel ouvrage": typescript, carbon, 1923 Aug (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Introduction à mes notes personnelles": typescript, carbon, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Introduction aux représentations de Tristan et Isolde à la Scala de Milan (1923-24), direction A. Toscanini": typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - " Lohengrin ": typescript, carbon, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "La mise en scène et son avenir, dédié aux élèves de l'institut Jaques-Dalcroze": typescript, carbon, 1921 Dec (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Monumentalité": typescript, carbon, 1922 Jul (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Die Musik und die Inscenierung, seconde préface à l'ouvrage: typescript, carbon, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Die Musik und die Inscenierung, English translation by Ulric Moore: bound typescript, carbon, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - La musique et la mise en scène, outline: typescript, photocopy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Notes de mise en scène für Den Ring des Nibelungen, 1891-1892": typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Notes sur le théâtre": typescript, carbon, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Réflexions sur l'espace et le temps": typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "La réforme et le théâtre de Bâle": typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Richard Wagner et la mise en scène": typescript, carbon, corrected, 1925 Mar (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Le sujet": typescript, carbon, 1922 Jan (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Writings About Appia, 1911-1971
  - "Adolphe Appia," exhibition pamphlet from the Victoria and Albert Museum, October 1970-January 1971: printed version, 1970-71 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Adolphe Appia: Über Ursprung und Anfang der rhythmischen Gymnastik": printed version, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Cahiers, section IV contains three articles on Appia: printed version, 1955 Jul (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Niessen, Carl, "Adolphe Appia: Goethes Faust, erster Teil, als Dichtung darge- stellt": printed version, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Odier, Henri, "Adolphe Appia: in memoriam": printed version, 1929 Mar (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Players Magazine, Adolphe Appia, 1862-1962, centenary issue: printed version, 1962 Jan (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Simonson, Lee, "Aesthetic Principles: The Ideas of Adolphe Appia": printed version, 1937 Jul (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Stadler, Edmund, "Adolphe Appia": printed version [German], 1959 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Stadler, Edmund, "Adolphe Appia": printed version [Italian], 1963 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Theatre Arts Monthly, Adolphe Appia, a memorial issue: printed version, 1932 Aug (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, "Adolphe Appia et Gordon Craig," extract from Musique après la Grande Guerre: typescript, carbon (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Van Wyck, Jessica Davis, "Designing Hamlet with Appia": typescript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Volbach, Walther R.
    - "Adolphe Appia," biographical entry in Allgemeine Enzyklopädie der Musik: printed version, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "Appia's Productions and Contem- porary Reaction": printed version, 1961 Mar (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "The Collaboration of Adolphe Appia and Emile Jaques-Dalcroze": printed version (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - "Jacques Copeau, Appia's Finest Disciple": printed version, 1965 Oct (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - "A Profile of Adolphe Appia": printed version, 1963 Mar (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Wolkonsky, Serge, "Conférence sur A. Appia": typescript, carbon, 1911 Nov 11 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Miscellaneous Papers, 1913-1924
  - Jaques-Dalcroze, Emile
    - Curriculum, institut Jaques- Dalcroze: brochure, printed version, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - "Der Rhythmus: Ein Jahrbuch her- ausgeg. von der Bildungsanstalt Jaques-Dalcroze, Dresden-Hellerau": pamphlet, printed version, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - "Le Rythme (méthode Jaques- Dalcroze)": pamphlet, printed version, 1924 Feb (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Photographs of Appia: reproductions, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Drawings, 1892-1896
  - "Valhalla," from Das Rheingold, scene 4, 1892 (Box 3 (Broadside))
  - "Rock of the Walkyries", 1892 (Box 4 (Broadside))
  - "Rock of the Walkyries", 1896 (Box 5 (Broadside))